Guide to the Montana Department of Natural Resources & Conservation From the Ground Up Oral History Project 2012-
Montana Historical Society Research Center
Montana Department of Natural Resources & Conservation From the Ground Up Oral History Project
2012 -
Montana Historical Society Archives
OH 2327
Montana. Deparment of Natural Resources & Conservation
041 .wav files Sound Recording 037 .pdf files Transcripts
37 audio recordings with transcripts; Number of sound files and pages in each transcript provided in container list.
This oral history project focused on the experiences of women who have operated farms and/or ranches in Montana during all or a portion of their life captured in 37 interviews. Each interview includes an audio recording and/or a typed transcript. You can find the transcripts on the DNRC Conservation Districts' Bureau Website.
Project History
The Montana Department of Natural Resources and Conservation Conservation Districts, Bureau, under the guidance of Linda Brander, developed the From the Ground Up Oral History Project in 2012 as a way to highlight the role of women in agriculture and conservation as an essential thread in the fabric of Montana's settlement and history. Working with local DNRC conservation districts, the program works with students, educators, and community leaders, providing training and guidance to local residents,520 teachers, and students as they prepare to conduct interviews. Interviews are then conducted with women in the local agricultural community.
Interviewers also included local conservation district administrators, and oral history project director Linda Brander. For more information on the project, please visit the Conservation Districts Bureau page on the Montana Department of Natural Resources and Conservation website.
This oral history project focused on the experiences of women who have operated farms and/or ranches in Montana during all or a portion of their life captured in 37 interviews. Each interview includes an audio recording and/or a typed transcript. You can find the transcripts on the DNRC Conservation Districts' Bureau Website.
This oral history project builds community memories by recording and preserving the oral histories of women ranchers and farmers. The stories capture a look at their past and a glimpse into their daily lives as they work and care for the land and animals. While each woman has a unique experience, a number of common topics are discussed in all the oral histories. These topics include what a typical day on the ranch/farm looks like, being a wife of a rancher/farmer and raising their families on ranches/farms, working as a family to operate the ranch/farm their involvement in their local communites, the community schools they attended as children, the link between ranching and conservation, how members of the agricultural community can strengthen ties with the public, what role they feel women play in agriculture, and what the term "sense of place" means to them.
Researchers requesting copies of interviews should refer to the OH number (OH 2327_##) and name of interviewee when ordering.
Inventory is arranged by item, with each oral history interview listed by its unique OH number.
Collection is open for research.
Linda Brander collected the interviews which were conducted by herself, Department of Natural Resources and Conservation Local Conservation District Managers, and members of the community.
You can find the transcripts on the DNRC Conservation Districts' Bureau Website.
This collection is indexed under the following headings. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search under these terms.
Montana. Deparment of Natural Resources & Conservation
Montana; Liberty County (Mont.); Toole County (Mont.); Carbon County (Mont.); Powell County (Mont.); Madison County (Mont.); Broadwater County (Mont.); Garfield County (Mont.); Big Horn County (Mont.); Roosevelt County (Mont.); Judith Basin County (Mont.); Sanders County (Mont.); Stillwater County (Mont.); Musselshell County (Mont.); Granite County (Mont.); Sweet Grass County (Mont.); Wibaux County (Mont.); Gallatin County (Mont.); Meagher County (Mont.)
Renewable natural resources--Montana; Women in agriculture--Montana; Range management--Montana; Families--Montana
Oral history; Sound recordings
Montana; Oral Histories; Sound Recordings; Home and Family
Detailed Description of the Collection
The following section contains a detailed listing of the materials in the collection
- EVELYN AIKEN INTERVIEW, 2014; OH 2327_1; 1 .wav file(s) Transcript 24 pages
  Evelyn Aiken was born January 24, 1925 in Whitlash, MT. Topics covered in the interview include: Whitlash (Mont.); Postmasters--Montana.; Chester (Mont.); Thompson Falls (Mont.)--schools.; Ranch life--winter.; Dowsing--Montana.; Weeds--Control--Montana.
- JEANETTE TOMSHECK BROWN INTERVIEW, 2015; OH 2327_2; 1 .wav file(s) Transcript 14 pages
  Jeanette Tomsheck Brown was born east of Sunburst, MT. Topics covered in the interview include: Sunburst (Mont.); Farm life--Winter.; Toole County (Mont.)--Schools.; Ranchers' spouses--Montana.; Whitlash (Mont.)--Presbyterian Church.
- CELESTE SCHWEND INTERVIEW, 2015; OH 2327_3; 1 .wav file(s) Transcript 13 pages
  Celeste Schwend (nee Ward) was born in Carbon County, MT on August 17, 1931. Topics covered in the interview include: Carbon County (Mont.)--Schools.; Carbon Conservation District; Dairy cattle--Montana.
- LINDA FINLEY INTERVIEW, 2015; OH 2327_4; 1 .wav file(s) Transcript 13 pages
  Linda Finley (nee Schwend) was born in Carbon County, MT on Pryor Mountain. Topics covered in the interview include: Carbon Count (Mont.)--Schools.; Ranch life--Montana.; Sheep industry--Montana.; Irrigation--Montana--Management.
- JOYCE VERNETTA LARSEN DYE INTERVIEW, 2015; OH 2327_5; 1 .wav file(s) Transcript 7 pages
  Joyce Vernetta Larsen Dye was born April 22, 1928 outside Galata, MT. Topics covered in the interview include: Farming activites--Harvesting.; Galata (Mont.)--Schools.
- MICHELLE GEARY HOLT INTERVIEW, 2013; OH 2327_6; 1 .wav file(s) Transcript 16 pages
  Michelle Geary Holt was born Jun 1948 in Butte, MT. Topics covered in the interview include: Helmville (Mont.)--History.; Ranchers' spouses--Montana.; Haying.; Haying equipment.; Cattle--Parturition.; Challenges--Ranch life.
- CORA GOGGINS AND JANET GOGGINS ENDECOTT INTERVIEW, 2012; OH 2327_7; 2 .wav file(s) Transcript 27 pages
  Cora Groggins was born in Harlowton, MT in 1929, Janet Groggins Endecott was born in 1944 in Ennis, MT. Topics covered in the interview include: Cattle--Breeding.; Cattle--Showing; Ranchers' spouses--Montana.; Ranches--Sexual division of labor.; Madison Conservation District.; Soil conservation--Montana.; Earthquakes--Montana--Hebgen Lake.
- DIANA GRAVELEY AND CHARMON GRAVELEY HANSEN INTERVIEW, 2013; OH 2327_8; 1 .wav file(s) Transcript 18 pages
  Diana Graveley (nee Burkart) was born in Billings, MT in 1928. Charmon Graveley Hansen grew up on the family ranch west of Canyon Ferry Lake, MT. Topics included in the interview include: Farm tenancy--Montana.; Agriculture--Economic aspects--Montana.; Ranchers' spouses--Montana.; Livestock farms--Montana.; Harvesting machinery.
- HELEN GIBBS INTERVIEW, 2015; OH 2327_9; 1 .wav file(s) Transcript 21 pages
  Helen Gibbs was born on August 19, 1928 in Jordan, MT. Topics covered in the interview include: Garfield County--Schools.; Jordan (Mont.); Predatory animals--Control--Montana.; Livestock--Grazing.; Rural electrification--Montana.
- MELODY HARDING INTERVIEW, 2013; OH 2327_10; 2 .wav file(s) Transcript 14 pages
  Melody Harding was born on February 24, 1951 in Lander, Wy. Topics covered in the interview include: Rodeos--Montana.; Horses--Training--Montana.; Ranches--Sexual division of labor.
- TRACY HENTGES INTERVIEW, 2014; OH 2327_11; 1 .wav file(s) Transcript 25 pages
  Tracy Hentges (nee Goerss) was born on March 2, 1964 in Springville, NY. Topics covered in the interview include: Cattle--Montana.; Wheat farmers--Montana.; Crops and soils--Montana.; Range management--Montana.
- BETTY HEDSTROM INTERVIEW, 2013; OH 2327_12; 2 .wav file(s) Transcript 25 pages
  Betty Johnson Hedstrom was born on February 13, 1955 in Great Falls, MT and raised in Raynesford, MT. Topics covered in the interview include: Fronteir and pioneer life--Homesteading--Montana.; Judith Basin (Mont.); Horse training--Montana.; Cattle--Montana.; 4-H clubs--Judith Basin (Mont.); Judith Basin Conservation District
- LAURAINE JOHNSON INTERVIEW, 2014; OH 2327_13; 2 .wav file(s) Transcript 23 pages
  Lauraine Johnson (nee Whitworth) was born on May 17, 1942 in Arlee, MT. Topics covered in the interview include: Farm tenancy--Montana.; Pastures--Irrigation.; Indians, North American--Montana--Ranching.; Eastern Sanders Conservation District; Resource Advisory Council
- MAGGIE JULSON INTERVIEW, 2014; OH 2327_14; 1 .wav file(s) Transcript 32 pages
  Maggie Julson (nee Small) was born July 27, 1942 in St. Charles, MN. She purchased her first Montana ranch in 1980 in Sheridan, MT and purchased a ranch in Reed Point, MT in 1989. Topics covered in the interview include: Sheep farming--Montana.; Grazing--Montana--Management.; Targhee Sheep; Alternative Energy Resources Organization (Helena, Mont.); Farming--No-tillage.; Predatroy animals--Contorl--Montana.
- JUDI KNAPP INTERVIEW, 2014; OH 2327_15; 1 .wav file(s) Transcript 12 pages
  Judi Knapp (nee Black) was born May 19, 1944 in New Rockford, ND and grew up on a rach in Musselshell County, MT. Topics covered in the interview include: Wheat farmers--Montana.; Challenges--Ranch life.; Ranches--Sexual division of labor.
- PEGGY GRAVELEY KUDE INTERVIEW, 2013; OH 2327_16; 1 .wav file(s) Transcript 9 pages
  Pegy Graveley Kude was born around 1941 andgrew up in Townsend, MT. Topics covered in the interview include: Townsend (Mont.); Hay--Harvesting.; Lombard (Mont.)--Schools
- ESTHER MCDONALD INTERVIEW, 2013; OH 2327_17; 1 .wav file(s) Transcript 21 pages
  Esther McDonalds was born in Seattle, WA and moved with her family to a ranch in Darby, MT. She then married her husband and moved onto his family ranch in Philipsburg, MT. Topics covered in the interview include: Livestock--Transportation.; Hay--Harvesting.; Pastures--Irrigation.; Women in agriculture--Montana--Societies, etc.; Ranching--Law and legislation; Montana Stockgrowers Association; Bitterroot Valley (Mont.)--Socieities, etc.; Social life and customs--Montana.
- NOLA PETERSON INTERVIEW, 2013; OH 2327_18; 1 .wav file(s) Transcript 7 pages
  Nola Peterson (Sorenson) was born on August 3, 1959 in Ontario, OR and ranches with her husband on the Person Grain and Cattle Inc. ranch 26 miles northwest of Havre, MT. Topics covered in the interview include: Farm management--Montana.; Wheat farmers--Montana. Community Activists--Hill County (Mont.)
- ARLENE PILE INTERVIEW, 2013; OH 2327_19; 1 .wav file(s) Transcript 10 pages
  Arlene Pile (nee Birkeland) was born on November 11, 1934 in Big Timber, MT and grew up on a ranch in Lower Deer Creek east of Big Timber. Topics covered in the interview include: Cattle--Montana.; Community Activists--Sweet Grass County (Mont.).
- VERNA SOKOLOSKI INTERVIEW, 2015; OH 2327_20; 1 .wav file(s) Transcript 27 pages
  Verna Sokoloski was born December 9, 1914 in Wibaus County, MT on the family ranch. Topics covered in the interview include: Social life and customs--Wibaux County (Mont.); Agriculture--Montana; Great Depression.; Icehouses--Montana.; Threshing--Montana.; St. Phillips (Mont.)--Schools.
- GLENNA STUCKY INTERVIEW, 2014; OH 2327_21; 1 .wav file(s) Transcript 12 pages
  Glenna Stucky (nee Krueger) was born September 21, 1936 in Bozeman, MT and grew up on a farm in the Gallatin Valley. Topics covered in the interview include: Farm management--Montana--Accounting.; Women in agriculture--Montana--Societies, etc.
- JANET ZEIG INTERVIEW, 2014; OH 2327_22; 2 .wav file(s) Transcript 24 pages
  Janet Zeig (nee Cameron) was born on April 22, 1934 In Harlow, MT and grew up on a ranch outside Martinsdale, MT. Topics covered in the interview include: Meagher County (Mont.)--Schools.; Wheatland County (Mont.)--School.; Sheep farming--Montana.; Grazing--Montana--Management.; Challenges--Ranch life.; Cattle--Animal feeding.; Livestock management--Montana.; Outfitting industry--Montana.; Ranches--Sexual division of labor.
- DANA WEATHERFORD INTERVIEW, 2015; OH 2327_23; 1 .wav file(s) Transcript 7 pages
  Dana Weatherford was born on July 17, 1993 in Billings, MT and spent her childhood on the family ranch in Joliet, MT. She is the daughter of Linda Finley (OH 2327_4). Topics covered in the interview include: Youth organizations--Agriculture.; Weeds--Control--Montana.
- LEE JACOBSEN INTERVIEW, 2014; OH 2327_24; 1 .wav file(s) Transcript 22 pages
  Mary Lee "Lee" Jacobsen was born on August 16, 1931 in La Push, WA and came to Conrad, MT following nursing school where she met and married her husband before purchasing a ranch outside Cut Bank, MT. Topics covered in the interview include: Artificial insemination industry, Cattle--Montana.; Oil wells--Montana--History--20th century.; Homesteading--Toole County (Mont.).; Homesteading--Pondera County (Mont.).; Challenges--Ranch life.; Irrigation--Montana--Management.; Soil conservation--Montana.
- BARBARA KIRSCHER INTERVIEW, 2014; OH 2327_25; 1 .wav file(s) Transcript 11 pages
  Barbara Kirscher was born April 15, 1927 in Judith Gap. Barbara Kirscher discusses her general feeling on conservation in regards to farming and ranching in the state. Topics covered in the interview include: Canton (Mont.); Irrigation--Management--Montana.; Flood control--Montana.
- PAULINE WEBB INTERVIEW, 2014; OH 2327_26; 1 .wav file(s) Transcript 15 pages
  Pauline Webb (nee Adams) was born August 28, 1920 and grew up in Iowa. Topics covered in the interview include: Ranchers' spouses--Montana.; Challenges--Ranch life.; Ranch life--Chores.; Agriculture in Montana Schools.
- VALERIE WADMAN INTERVIEW, 2016; OH 2327_27; 1 .wav file(s) Transcript 14 pages
  Valerie Wadman was born in Seattle, WA in 1947. In 1970 she married and moved onto a ranch near Cut Bank, MT. In the intreview Ms. Wadman discusses both her own ranching experiences, as well as those of her grandparents who homesteaded in Montana in the 1910s. Topics covered in the interview include: Internship programs--Agriculture.; Tiber Dam effect on farms and ranches on the Marias River; Homesteading--Montana.; Sheep farming--Montana.
- COLLEEN MCGOWAN GUSTAFSON INTERVIEW, 2014; OH 2327_28; 1 .wav file(s) Transcript 22 pages
  Coleen McGowan Gustafson was born January 4, 1966 in Highwood, MT, and grew up farming and ranching on her family's ranch. She married and began ranching outside Browning, MT. Topics covered in the interview include: Hihgwood School; 4-H clubs--Highwood (Mont.); Ranchers' spouses--Montana.; Cattle--Montana.; Livestock--Bottle feeing.; Challenges--Ranch life.; Weeds--Control--Montana.; Predatory animals--Control--Montana.; Livestock--Grazing.
- LELA "CORKY" FRENCH INTERVIEW, 2015; OH 2327_29; 1 .wav file(s) Transcript 19 pages
  Lela "Corky" French was bork June 7, 1939 on the family farm in Philips County, MT. She and her husband, Bill French (included in the interview), now run French Farms in Phipips County, a three generational hay farm and cattle ranch operation. Topics covered in the interview include: 4-H clubs--Philips County (Mont.); Soil conservation--Montana.; Rural Electric Administration--Montana.; Bureau of Land Management--Grazing system.; Farming--Hay--Montana.
- EVA AMUNDSON INTERVIEW, 2016; OH 2327_30; 1 .wav file(s) Transcript 37 pages
  Eva Amundson was born April 23, 1911 near Langdon, ND. Her great-nephew, Sigurd Jensen, was involved in the interview. her family ran a dry land farm outside Joplin, MT. In 1930 she married Lief Norman in Hill County, MT. Topics covered in the interview include: Opportunity Resources.; Farm management--Montana--Sexual division of labor.; Fronteir and pioneer life--Homesteading --Montana.; Joplin (Mont.)--Schools.; Social life and customs--Montana.; Crop losses-- Montana.; strip farming.; Farming--Method & application--Development.
- DONNA GRIFFIN INTERVIEW, 2015; OH 2327_31; 1 .wav file(s) Transcript 12 pages
  Donna Griffin was raised on a farm in the Chester, MT area. Topics covered in the interview include: Farming activites--Harvesting.; Wheat farmers--Montana.; Grain farmers--Montana.; Soil conservation--Montana.; Farming--Method & application--Development.; Challenges--Ranch life.
- JEAN WALDBILLIG INTERVIEW, 2013; OH 2327_32; Transcript 35 pages
  Jean Waldbillig was born in Nevada and grew up in Philipsberg and Butte. After marriage she returned to Philipsburg with her husband where she worked as a Registered Nurse at the local hospital. Interview focuses mainly on the community of Philipsberg from the Great Depression on to more current times. Topics covered in the interview include: Farm management--Montana--Sexual division of labor.; Dairy cattle--Montana.; Cattle--Montana.; Social life and customs--Montana.
- MARGARET "PEGGY" FLOERSINGER INTERVIEW, 2016; OH 2327_33; 1 .wav file(s) Transcript 9 pages
  This interview highlights Margaret Floersinger’s experiences farming and ranching near Conrad, Montana. The oral history provides fascinating details about Margaret’s early life in England, her move to Montana after World War II, and her life raising a family in rural Montana. Margaret’s experiences help provide a much clearer understanding of the important role women have played in Montana’s agricultural and ranching history.
- ANDREA OLENIK INTERVIEW, 2016; OH 2327_34; 1 .wav file(s) Transcript 15 pages
  This interview highlights the life experiences of Andrea Olenik, who was 95 years old at the time of the interview. The oral history covers her formative years growing up in Montana, marriage in 1939, and raising three children on a farm near Hardin, Montana. Andrea’s history covers nearly ten decades and provides a valuable understanding of the important role women have played in Montana’s agricultural and ranching history.
- BARB HABETS INTERVIEW, 2016; OH 2327_35; 1 .wav file(s) Transcript 5 pages
  Barb Habets grew up in Lewistown, MT and began farming in Conrad, MT after marrying her husband. Topics covered in the interview include: Soil conservation--Montana.; Farm management--Montana--Sexual division of labor.
- BONNIE KRONEBUSCH INTERVIEW, 2016; OH 2327_36; 1 .wav file(s) Transcript 5 pages
  Bonnie Kronebusch was born 1949 in Valier, MT where her family had a farm and eventually began farming with her husband outside Conrad, MT. Topics covered in the interview include: Farm management--Montana--Sexual division of labor.; Social life and customs--Montana.; Home and family--Montana.; Soil conservation--Montana.
- DORIS BISHOP INTERVIEW, 2016; OH 2327_37; 1 .wav file(s) Transcript 6 pages
  This interview highlights Doris Bishop’s experiences farming and ranching near Brady, Montana. The oral history provides fascinating details about Doris’s childhood living on a homestead in Montana during the 1930s-1940s and later raising her own family in rural Montana. Doris’s experiences help provide a much clearer understanding of the important role women have played in Montana’s agricultural and ranching history.